<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<calendar>
<event>
<title>Maja Mataric, University of Southern California</title>
<date>2013-06-07</date>
<startTime>11:00:00</startTime>
<endTime>12:00:00</endTime>
<contact>Carolyn M. Simpson cmsimpso@ics.uci.edu</contact>
<location>Donald Bren Hall 3011 Note: Room Change to 3011</location>
<description><p><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;">Maja Mataric<br />University of Southern California</span></p><p><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;"></span><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;">TITLE: </span></strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;"><span> </span>Human-Machine Interaction Methods for Socially Assistive Robotics</span></p><p><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;">ABSTRACT:</span></strong></p><p><strong></strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;">Socially assistive robotics (SAR) is a new field of intelligent robotics that focuses on developing machines capable of assisting users through social rather than physical interaction. The robot&rsquo;s physical embodiment is at the heart of SAR&rsquo;s effectiveness, as it leverages the inherently human tendency to engage with lifelike (but not necessarily human-like or otherwise biomimetic) social behavior. People readily ascribe intention, personality, and emotion to robots; SAR leverages this engagement stemming from non-contact social interaction involving speech, gesture, movement demonstration and imitation, and encouragement, to develop robots capable of monitoring, motivating, and sustaining user activities and improving human learning, training, performance and health outcomes. Human-robot interaction (HRI) for SAR is a growing multifaceted research area at the intersection of engineering, health sciences, neuroscience, social, and cognitive sciences.   This talk will describe our research into embodiment, modeling and steering social dynamics, and long-term user adaptation for SAR. The research will be grounded in projects involving analysis of multi-modal activity data, modeling personality and engagement, formalizing social use of space and non-verbal communication, and personalizing the interaction with the user over a period of months, among others. The presented methods and algorithms will be validated on implemented SAR systems evaluated by<span class="apple-style-span"> human subject cohorts from a variety of user populations, including stroke patients, children with autism spectrum disorder, and elderly with Alzheimers and other forms of dementia.  </span></span></p><p><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;"></span><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;"> </span></strong><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;">BIO:</span></strong></p><p><strong></strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;">Maja Mataric&acute; is professor and Chan Soon-Shiong chair in Computer Science, Neuroscience, and Pediatrics at the University of Southern California, founding director of the USC Center for Robotics and Embedded Systems (cres.usc.edu), co-director of the USC Robotics Research Lab (robotics.usc.edu) and Vice Dean for Research in the USC Viterbi School of Engineering. She received her PhD in Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence from MIT in 1994, MS in Computer Science from MIT in 1990, and BS in Computer Science from the University of Kansas in 1987. She is a Fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), Fellow of the IEEE, and recipient of the Presidential Awards for Excellence in Science, Mathematics &amp; Engineering Mentoring (PAESMEM), the </span><a href="http://anitaborg.org/"><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;"><font color="#660000">Anita Borg Institute</font></span></a><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;"> </span><a href="http://anitaborg.org/initiatives/women-of-vision/"><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;"><font color="#660000">Women of Vision Award</font></span></a><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;"> for Innovation, Okawa Foundation Award, NSF Career Award, the MIT TR100 Innovation Award, and the IEEE Robotics and Automation Society Early Career Award. She served as the elected president of the USC faculty and the Academic Senate. At USC she has been awarded the Viterbi School of Engineering Service Award and Junior Research Award, the Provost&#39;s Center for Interdisciplinary Research Fellowship, the Mellon Mentoring Award, the Academic Senate Distinguished Faculty Service Award, and a Remarkable Woman Award. She is featured in the science documentary movie &quot;Me &amp; Isaac Newton&quot;, in The New Yorker (&quot;Robots that Care&quot; by Jerome Groopman, 2009), Popular Science (&quot;The New Face of Autism Therapy&quot;, 2010), the IEEE Spectrum (&quot;Caregiver Robots&quot;, 2010), and is one of the LA Times Magazine 2010 Visionaries. Prof. Mataric&acute; is an associate editor of three major journals and has published extensively. She serves or has recently servied on a number of advisory boards, including the National Science Foundation Computing and Information Sciences and Engineering (CISE) Division Advisory Committee, and the Willow Garage and Evolution Robotics Scientific Advisory Boards. Prof. Mataric&acute; is actively involved in K-12 educational outreach, having obtained federal and corporate grants to develop free open-source curricular materials for elementary and middle-school robotics courses in order to engage student interest in science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) topics. Her Interaction Lab&#39;s research into socially assistive robotics is aimed at endowing robots with the ability to help people through individual non-contact assistance in convalescence, rehabilitation, training, and education. Her research is currently developing robot-assisted therapies for children with autism spectrum disorders, stroke and traumatic brain injury survivors, and individuals with Alzheimer&#39;s Disease and other forms of dementia. Details about her research are found at </span><a href="http://robotics.usc.edu/interaction"><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;"><font color="#660000">http://robotics.usc.edu/interaction/</font></span></a><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: &#39;Arial&#39;,&#39;sans-serif&#39;">.</span></p></description>
</event>
<event>
<title>FRIDAY INFORMATICS SEMINAR, co-sponsored by COR, the Center for Organizational Research: Andrew Penner, School of Social Sciences, UCI - June 7th, 2013, DBH 6011</title>
<date>2013-06-07</date>
<startTime>15:00:00</startTime>
<endTime>17:00:00</endTime>
<contact>Annie Harnack aharnack@ics.uci.edu</contact>
<location>6011 Donald Bren Hall </location>
<description>FRIDAY INFORMATICS SEMINAR <br />Co-sponsored by COR, the Center for Organizational Research <br /> <br />Andrew Penner <br />School of Social Sciences <br />University of Irvine, CA <br />Date: Friday, June 7, 2013 <br />Talk: 3:00 PM <br />Location: 6011 Donald Bren Hall <br />Refreshments: 4:15 PM, to be served in the 5th floor lobby. <br /> <br />Title: <br />Refusing to fail: Over-persistence, under-persistence, and the gender  gap in science <br /> <br />Abstract: <br />Research on gender differences in science, technology, engineering, and  mathematics (STEM) fields typically focuses on the under-representation  of women, attributing gender differences to factors like the chilly  climate in these fields and women&rsquo;s choices to avoid STEM. The present  study extends this literature in two ways. First, we examine where women  who leave STEM fields go, and whether their choices to opt out of STEM  should be conceptualized as under-persistence. Second, we examine  whether men persist excessively in the face of negative feedback in  these same fields. Using a novel experimental paradigm, we find evidence  that men tended to choose mathematics over verbal questions in a testing  environment where the mathematics problems were extremely difficult and  they were paid for performance. Corroborating evidence of this male  &ldquo;over-persistence effect&rdquo; is also found in college STEM course-taking  behavior, where men are more likely to re-take STEM courses after  failing them. <br /> <br />Bio <br />Andrew Penner is currently an assistant professor in the Department of  Sociology at the University of California, Irvine, where he is a member  of the Irvine Network on Interventions in Development. He is also a  faculty affiliate of the Master of Public Policy program, the UC  Educational Evaluation Center, the Center for Demographic and Social  Analysis, and the Center for Organizational Research. His research  examines gender, race, and family inequality in education and the labor  market, and how physical characteristics are translated into social  inequality. He is currently involved in projects examining the role of  marriage and children in creating gender wage inequality in Norway, the  implications of racial fluidity for inequality in the United States, and  the over-representation of men in mathematics and the sciences. </description>
</event>
<event>
<title>TOP TRENDS IN TECH SPEAKER SERIES - Thornton May</title>
<date>2013-06-11</date>
<startTime>17:00:00</startTime>
<endTime>18:00:00</endTime>
<contact>Robert Farmer rfarmer@ics.uci.edu</contact>
<location>Bren Hall 6011 </location>
<description><span style="border-collapse: collapse; color: #152745; font-size: 13px; -webkit-border-horizontal-spacing: 2px; -webkit-border-vertical-spacing: 2px" class="Apple-style-span"><div class="date_location" style="color: #5f595a">JUNE 11, Tuesday, 5 to 6 p.m. <br />Beckman Center</div></span><span style="border-collapse: collapse; color: #152745; font-size: 13px; -webkit-border-horizontal-spacing: 2px; -webkit-border-vertical-spacing: 2px" class="Apple-style-span"><div class="date_location" style="color: #5f595a"> </div><div class="talk_title" style="font-size: 14px; padding-top: 0.5em; padding-right: 0px; padding-bottom: 0.5em; padding-left: 0px">&ldquo;THE HIGH PERFORMANCE ORGANIZATION OF 2025&rdquo;</div><div class="speaker_name_title" style="font-weight: bold">THORNTON MAY <br />Futurist, Executive Director and Dean &mdash; IT Leadership Academy</div><div class="speaker_info">The editors at eWeek have included May on their list of Top 100 Most Influential People in IT, while the editors at Fast Company have labeled him &ldquo;one of the top 50 brains in business.&rdquo;</div></span></description>
</event>
</calendar>